[Music]
Welcome to the Business Central launch
edition of 2025 release wave 2 for
finance analytics.
A recent survey from IDC uh where they
surveyed smallmedium business customers
unlocked an insights that I thought was
interesting. Um they were asked about
different things. One of the things they
were asked was immediate business
priorities of top five. Um, and what
they answered in both the small and
medium segment of of customers was that
profitability and process efficiency
those were both in the top five.
So when planning for this wave for
finance analytics, we thought let's try
to make those two a focus area for what
we do in finance analytics.
The highlights of uh that area, we can't
show everything in this video. It's
simply too much. But um we have these
four kind of investment areas. financial
reporting, deferral analysis,
documentation and PowerBI app for
finance.
For the first one, financial reporting.
This is something we know from our
telemetry that this is used for by more
than a third of all customers uh use
this. And uh in this release, we want to
give you some productivity improvements
because yeah, we like that you use the
feature. Here's something that make it
even easier to use financial reporting.
Um, but in particular also some larger
improvements that you can um make
financial statements that yeah fit your
needs. And uh for the second part, we
made it easier to analyze deferrals both
posted and upcoming. So I'll show you
that. Um, with our upcoming or with our
improved documentation,
we uh we also uh hopefully it has never
been easier to both discover and
understand uh the breadth of out of the
box reports that exist for Business
Central and simply something that you
can hopefully use if you're not already
using them to make your finance
department uh more data driven. And
finally, speaking of of datadriven, the
enhanced PowerBI for finance. Uh here we
added uh things to help you get to
analyze to get a better cash flow both
for analyzing late payments and also
help you in general with your accounts
receivables historical analysis. So
should we dive in? I think we should. So
for financial reporting, here are the
highlights. The two highlights are
dynamic date headers and ability to run
reports that both show amounts in in uh
local currency and additional uh
reporting currency. And then we have
some small enhancements that I will kind
of show you in the demo as well.
So here in business central I have
opened the financial reporting list page
and if we just choose the first account
categories overview report and view that
uh this report if you see the options
here you can see the
show more uh you can see that this
report is using the periods column
definition and the periods column
definition is showing you current period
current period minus one and current
period minus2, right?
That's probably written by an engineer.
No, just a joke. Uh because we didn't
actually have a way to to specify like
minus1 and minus2. You really want to
see what period you are on here, right?
So that's something that we changed. You
also uh if you look carefully, one of
the the small productivity improvements
we did was that the show less show more
is is hiding a few more of the fields
that you don't really need to see when
you're already consuming the report. So
that gives you a little bit more screen
size to see the actual report. So could
we do anything about this current period
uh thing? Let's try to go to definitions
and edit the column definition. the
period column definition. Small
productivity improvement here is that
you can also now change the column
description directly from the card. In
the previous release, you had to do that
on the lists. Anyway, uh we have a new
option here called include date in
column header. So that means instead of
calling this current period, I could
actually say current period and then
specify I would like here to see the
month. And then if I do that, I could
just get rid of the column headers
completely and just choose to show the
month here. Okay, that's it. Let's go
back to the account categories overview
here and view it again. And what you
notice here is now the column headers is
showing current period. That was the
only thing in the text. But now we have
in parenthesis September. Um that means
when we have both a text and a date part
of the header, we put the date heart
date part in parenthesis. But the other
two here where there's only a a date
component is just shown with with that.
So that's uh that's dynamic uh date uh
headers uh for your reports. Okay. So
the other thing is the report that
supports additional reporting
currencies. Let's just go back to the
the column definition and see how that
works. Um, if I scroll this to the
right, there's a new column here called
show in uh ACY in additional reporting
currency. And if I do that, maybe not on
the periods, but let's pick a different
uh one. Let's pick maybe the balance
definition. So, if I go here, edit
column definitions for balance. I could
have another one that says balance in
additional currency. Maybe I should have
uh this as balance at date. And then I
can simply choose the ladder here to
show in additional uh currency. Now I
haven't set up this system to actually
use uh additional currency. So this will
show up blank but I can show you in the
end of the presentation how that looks.
If I just do it here, you see that uh
since ACI is not set up, I just have uh
blanks. But if if that was set up, I
would have the same amount in the two
different currencies.
What else did we do? So, um for row
definitions
here
um in the past, if I wanted to change
the description, I had to edit it here.
So, a new thing, if I edit my row
definition, I can just like columns, I
can change the description here. Another
thing that we did was we made it
possible to edit the row definitions in
Excel because row definitions are very
much like tied to a way to work with
rows in Excel. So, so that's just a
small productivity improvement.
Um, another thing we did was for row
definitions. Let's say I want to add a
posting account and I want to add a
single account. See if I can find one
here.
If I do that,
then you notice that the description
directly in my row definition is just
autocompleted. So if you add a single GL
account here in the row definition, uh
that description is transferred over.
You can still of course change it to
whatever you want, but but that's a nice
little shortcut.
A final small improvement is if you
change the name of a deal account, let's
just take Goodwill and edit this. Then
since GL accounts can be used in
financial reporting, um if you change
the name here, you might also want to
change a name somewhere. So, if I change
this to, I don't know, Goodwills,
um, I will get a notification, a new one
here, that I changed a GL account, and I
might want to check if I'm using this
account in any financial report where
the name should be changed as well. All
right, so let me I promised to show you
a picture at least of the financial
report with additional uh reporting
currency. So let me go back to the
presentation and just show that and move
on to deferrals.
Yeah. And as I promised here is the
balance sheet financial report but with
a column definition that now have
additional currency on a system where
additional currency is enabled. So now
you have your balance both in the local
currency and your additional reporting
currency. The next um is PowerBI for
finance. So the story here is that we
wanted to make it much easier for
controllers, CFOs, finance people to
analyze age receivables and in
particular late payments uh because both
of these are something that uh impact
your cash flow. So a few improvements in
the PowerBI app for that. Uh let's show
let me show you that. So the first
addition is a completely new report late
payment analysis on receivables and um I
really like I think this is one of the
key things we added uh in this release
for for for analytics um among the
things we did in purchasing app but I I
I think this is this is pretty cool. So
the visual you see here the bubble
charts is like normally BI or reporting
is very much like you see tabular things
or you see like a bar chart or something
but but here we actually are able to see
late payments by size right so so what
what you see here is late payment
amounts which means the amount that is
outstanding is on this axis and the the
lateness or the average days late is is
here on the second axis. And when then
we simply plot your customers or you get
a plot of your customers where the size
of the bubbles is kind of the the size
of uh of the amount, right? So that
means the further you are up here um if
you're up here that's bad, right?
because that means this is a customer
that has like a large amount late
payment and is also like one of the most
late payers. Right? So if I look at Trey
I can see that uh yeah they have 10,000
outstanding on average 15 days and with
six payments that are late. If I choose
this bubble here everything changes. So
you can see the uh the navigation here
is uh is that all the KPIs are of course
filtered to that. But you can also now
see that uh even though it's bad with
Trey, it's actually getting better,
right? So here's your monthly uh late
payments over time. And you can see that
even though they are late paying pay
paying they were actually much more um
or actually the late payments are like
something is outstanding from January
6,000 uh 2,000 last month and so on. And
you can also directly see the
transaction. So if you want to go back
in business central and check out the
different uh invoices uh you could do
that. So hopefully this will give you
like a one-stop shop to analyze late
payments and of then you should annotate
this analytics with processes in your AP
or in your finance so that you also or
AR sorry so that you also kind of know
how to follow up with uh with Trey and
others. So that was the first thing for
cash flow. The second thing is under the
average collection period report. So um
this looks like the one you know except
that you now also have a historical
trend. So an average collection period
average uh one year uh ahead or behind
and and that means that you can kind of
see for instance here that you have
collections like amounts due but then
because you look back in time then this
particular graph only jumps when you
have kind of accumulated accounts
receivable. So this was an idea we had
from one of you that wanted a report on
exactly this and we thought it instead
of writing a new report in business
central we just added this ability to
the to the collection period uh report
in PowerBI. So for deferrals in finance,
I mean deferring uh either um sales
purchases, purchase invoices or even
just on a GL level. Uh you now have the
ability to analyze upcoming which means
non-posted and existing deferrals,
deferrals that are posted. Uh the latter
was the only thing you you could do um
before this release. We also modernized
the report layouts so that they now use
Word or Excel. So that means if you
don't like the layouts we provide, you
can just use either word or excel to
change it to the format that you like.
And then we also added inclient
documentation and articles on learn how
to use um reporting for deferrals.
So um here's an example of the deferral
summary. It's an existing report but we
added these new layout. You can see that
when you open the request page that um
you get if you open the the layout
option here in the request page you can
choose between word and excel. RDLC is
the one that will be deprecated of these
layouts. So you could if if you normally
just have want a PDF, you probably want
word to be the default. If you only only
want to analyze this in Excel, you can
set the Excel layout to the default. um
and then it will respect that on the
request page. As with all reports, you
also get the teaching tips uh with links
to documentation. So, so that we try to
explain what this report is for. And in
the documentation if I choose this
particular learn link oh in 2 minutes.
Um so the the layout first is the the
before layout in RDL
just the technology we use for layouts
in the past for the printable version.
You can see the the pre and post. So now
the word layout you can see it it's the
same right? It's it it doesn't really
change anything. So it doesn't break
anything. If you like uh the PDF, you
you keep doing it just with a different
way of rendering the PDF. But for Excel,
this is this is also new. Um you now
they have the ability to analyze across
every deferral whether it's one report
for each. So for sales, uh purchase or
GL. Uh so now you can slice and dice,
filter. Uh you can even make these Excel
layouts your own and then upload them
and make them um the defaults that that
you like.
Um as a new feature, we also added three
new pages, deferral lines for sales,
purchase and GL so that you can um
analyze the deferral lines across all
unposted documents. In the in the
previous release, you would the only way
to do this would be to go into each
invoice and look at the deferral
schedule, but now you have that across
and you can analyze all the deferrals uh
that will be when like unposted
deferrals across all invoices and that
uh you just take these pages the these
line pages into analysis mode and then
you can you can analyze away.
Right.
Final thing in the presentation and then
you're off the hook is an completely new
documentation of finance reports along
the lines of VAT cost accounting
deferrals consolidations and in inter
company we added both learn content and
these incline teaching tips for all of
that. And you might think like who
cares? Um well, I've had um partners
reach out to me that that they when they
saw this that they said, "Oh, um
actually, we didn't know that the um
whatever it is, let's say um deferrals
or um cost accounting. We didn't know
that this feature had reports uh because
we kind of we as Microsoft forgot or uh
forgot or didn't have time to document
this. So now it's here under finance
reports uh for all these reports uh both
an overview of what is available and for
each of these also documentation uh for
each report stating what the report
shows uh some use case of the report and
then of course a link back to business
central. So hopefully this opens up for
um a lot of reporting that you did not
know exists and hopefully that can make
you a lot more data driven as a finance
department.
If you want to learn more about
analytics in finance, this is your
landing page aka.ms/bc
finance analytics. It takes you through
everything there is to know about
financial reporting, PowerBI for
finance, built-in uh reports, the chart
of accounts, uh reporting capabilities
and and so on. So if you work with
finance, definitely go bookmark this uh
landing page and learn how you can be a
lot more datadriven uh in the finance
department.
That's it. Um, just three more links and
then you are off the hook. So, LinkedIn,
if you're not uh already following the
product group on LinkedIn, you should
definitely do that if you want to stay
ahead of the game on the news around our
product. Aka.ms/bc
LinkedIn is where you uh that takes you
to the LinkedIn profile and then you
just follow and then you get news about
things that are coming. Um, yeah, on a
pretty regular basis likely. very very
likely like weekly
since you're watching this on YouTube um
you probably know our YouTube channel uh
if not aka.ms/bc
YouTube is takes you takes you there
bookmark it has a lot more than launch
edition videos uh we have like tips and
tricks uh co-pilot and AI videos deep
dives uh even under the hood which is uh
like a series of things that are coming
in the next release way before it it
hits the the release plans. So, um, if
that's not enough for you, we have some
more AKA links as well. The first one,
aka.ms/bc
all is similar to Lord of the Rings.
This is the AKA link to rule them all.
Every AKA link that is relevant for a
partner uh is is on that landing page.
So, bookmark that. If you're a business
central partner and if you're not yet on
Yammer, please uh join us there on aka
like aka.ms/bc
yammer. This is where we have
conversations, discussions, questions
about the product. No customers are are
there. So sorry if you are a customer.
This is only for partners. Uh the final
link I want to highlight is the office
hours aka.ms/bc
office hours. We have typically every
month an office hour call. This is both
for customers and partners on something
that is relevant to the future of the
product. Um so go check that out and
maybe uh join one of our office hours.
With that I thank you for uh for
watching and I hope you get much more
datadriven with your finances. Uh I'm
done for now. Thank you.